NYSUT President's Office Files. 6174/001
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Series Presidents files: Subseries 2
  - Buffalo Teachers Federation, 1974 (Box 41, Folder 10)
    Letters re internal staffing changes related to UniServ; newspaper clipping from Buffalo Evening News re charges by NEA team of segregation at school district (received Jan. 18, 1974); memo re procedures for special election, January 18, 1973; correspondence between NYSUT president Tom Hobart and BTF president Tom Pisa re additional funding from NYSUT, December 1973-January 1974
  - Buffalo Teachers Federation, 1973 (Box 41, Folder 11)
    Copy of United Teachers of Buffalo newsletter Buffalo Teacher front page, featuring article, "How Much Longer Can Buffalo Teachers Afford Ineffective Leadership?" criticizing BTF president Tom Pisa for leading Buffalo teachers out of NYSUT into the "tiny, floundering state organization known as NYEA," with graph comparing Consumer Price Index to salary teacher increases, August 1975- June 1981 (projected), April 1980; Buffalo Public Schools newsletter, outlining superintendent's priorities for the new school year, September 1973; unsigned document, "The Genesis and Pioneer Days of the Buffalo Teachers' Federation," n.d.; correspondence between NYSUT president Tom Hobart and BTF president Tom Pisa re support for field service operation, July 1973
  - Buffalo Teachers Federation, 1972 (Box 41, Folder 12)
    BTF audit of monies in lieu of services, December 6, 1973; correspondence re financial matters; briefing letter to Toni Cortese and others re Buffalo Teachers Federation and relationship with school district, n.d.
  - Buffalo Teachers Federation, 1970-1971 (Box 41, Folder 13)
    Text of speech given by president Tom Pisa at meeting of BTF Council of Delegates re negotiations with school district, September 17, 1971; handwritten notes re strike, PERB decision; letter to parents from Tom Pisa, president of BTF, faulting mayor for failing to provide local Board of Education with sufficient funds, June 24, 1971; survey of BTF members as to course of action; public relations recommendations; correspondence re participation in NEA-sponsored voter registration drive, December 1970-April 1971; correspondence between executive secretary of New York State Teachers Association (NYSTA) and Tom Pisa as official of NYS Urban Coalition (consisting of presidents of teachers associations in Buffalo, Rochester, and Syracuse), re purported insensitivity of NYSTA toward needs of urban school districts, January-May, 1971; drafts of memoranda of agreement between BTF and NYSTA
  - Buffalo Teachers Federation Contracts and Constitution, 1971-1976 (Box 41, Folder 14)
    Constitution of Buffalo Teachers Federation, Inc., as amended January 23, 1975; arbitration agreement between Buffalo Teachers Federation, the Buffalo Board of Education, and Public Employment Relations Board (PERB), commencing September 27, 1976, and expiring June 30, 1978; master contracts between the Board of Education of the City of Buffalo and the Buffalo Teachers Federation, November 1967 (revised January 1971), 1972-73, and July 1, 1973 - June 30, 1976
  - Buffalo Teachers Federation Executive Committee, 1973-1976 (Box 41, Folder 15)
    List of members of Executive Committee, with addresses, c. 1975-76; agenda for Council of Delegates meeting of February 28, 1974; Executive Committee minutes of April 9, 1975; memo to delegates and alternates re proposed amendments to constitution, February 14, 1974; minutes of Council of Delegates meeting of January 17, 1974; minutes of Executive Committee meeting of June 21, 1973; meeting notices
  - Buffalo Teachers Federation Council of Delegates, 1975-1977 (Box 41, Folder 16)
    Newsletter, BTF Leadership Edition, January 1977; procedures for electing delegates to the Constitutional Convention and 1977 NYEA Convention; meeting notices
  - Buffalo Teachers Federation Provocator, 1972-1979 (Box 41, Folder 17)
    Official publication of the Buffalo Teachers Federation, Inc.
  - NEA Termination File, 1976 (Box 41, Folder 18)
    Confidential envelope with offers of employment, handwritten notes comparing expenses (including salaries) of NYSUT vs. NYEA (minimal); New York Educators Association Tentative Budget Program, 1976-77 Fiscal Year, showing scenarios for minimal program (94 staff) at $65 dues, full program (118 staff) at $65 dues, full program - operating expenses - budget projections, full program - budget and staffing by service function, minimal program - staffing by service function, and revenue analysis; related strategic memo to Ken (Melley?) from Bob (Manners?), June 22, 1976; draft of letter to treasurer of NEA from NYSUT secretary-treasurer noting that the NYSUT Representative Assembly voted to disaffiliate with NEA, that termination notice had been given on January 14, 1976, that acceptance by NEA had been ratified, and that the 60-day notice would expire on March 16, 1976; memo re draft letter from NYSUT legal counsel, advising change in date of expiration of notice to March 14, January 20, 1976; memos re NEA dues, February-March 1976
  - NEA Membership Dues Correspondence, 1974-1976 (Box 41, Folder 19)
    Memo outlining procedure for collection of dues owed to NEA, noting that NYSUT was not yet officially disaffiliated from NEA, as all the necessary steps had not yet been completed, March 29, 1976; letter from NYSUT president Tom Hobart to NEA president John Royer, remarking that his recent communications were most disturbing, clarifying that NYSUT Representative Assembly had not voted to disaffiliate from NEA, only that it removed mandate to affiliate from constitution, March 19, 1976; letter from Royer to Hobart re dues, March 11, 1976; related Western Union mailgrams; letter from Hobart to NYSUT locals explaining change to constitution; handwritten notes calculating NEA dues
  - NEA Dues Transmittal Agreement, 1975-1976 (Box 41, Folder 20)
    Membership and Dues Transmittal Procedure Data Processing System, National Education Association, January 1974; Agreement between the NEA and New York State United Teachers Regarding the Collection and Transmission of NEA Dues and Membership Data (unsigned); correspondence between legal and financial officers of NEA and NYSUT
  - NEA Dues Agreement Termination Letters, 1974-1976 (Box 41, Folder 21)
    Letter from NYSUT president Tom Hobart to NEA associate director of business and financial management Don Arbogast, disagreeing with claim of financial obligation of NYSUT to NEA, noting that NEA had unilaterally and wrongfully terminated NYSUT's status as an NEA affiliate, June 17, 1976; letter from NYSUT secretary-treasurer Ed Rogers to NEA business and financial officer Roger Montgomery, informing him of intention by NYSUT to terminate agreement between NYSUT and NEA, January 14, 1976; letter from NYSUT attorney to NEA attorney, noting revised dues transmittal agreement, December 30, 1975; related correspondence, disputing disaffiliation status; three copies of Agreement between the NEA and New York State United Teachers Regarding the Collection and Transmission of NEA Dues and Membership Data, signed by NEA executive director Terry Herndon, 12/30/75 (not signed by NYSUT); three copies of NEA memo to state staff - membership processing/dues accounting, with attached Membership and Dues Transmittal Procedure Data Processing System, National Education Association, January 1974
  - NEA Letters to Members, 1975 (Box 41, Folder 22)
    First draft, letter to NYSUT Board of Directors, recounting April 8 meeting of officers of NYSUT and NEA, cut short because of refusal by NEA to allow meeting to be tape recorded; letter from NEA president James A. Harris to NYSUT president Tom Hobart, disagreeing with factual account of April 8 meeting between NEA and NYSUT officers, April 30, 1975; open letter to NEA members in New York State from NEA president James A. Harris, accusing NYSUT of representing NEA to members in a negative light, with attached resolution passed by NEA Board of Directors, directing NEA executive secretary to "take such steps as he deems necessary to counteract" negative publicity by NYSUT, February 28, 1975; unsigned statement expressing shock by NYSUT over interference by NEA in internal operation of New York affiliate, specifically condemning the direct mailing by NEA president to members, warning of further action by NYSUT Board of Directors and Representative Assembly, March 20, 1975; New York Times clipping, "Teachers Now Lions in Political Arena," January 15, 1975, with cover memo to NEA Board of Directors, January 20, 1975; substitute motion affirming commitment by NYSUT to merger of all teachers into one national organization, requesting a meeting with NEA president between March 21-23, 1975, to discuss state of relations between NEA and NYSUT
  - Disaffiliation from NEA, 1975-1977 (Box 41, Folder 23)
    Letters between attorneys re NEA v. NYSUT, 1977; certified letter from NYSUT president Tom Hobart to NEA president John Royer re dues, with attached copy of check, September 22, 1976; letter from Royer to Hobart, informing him that NEA would proceed with prosecution to recover dues still claimed, October 1, 1976; letter from Tom Hobart to NEA state presidents (in other states) re NEA "vendetta" in New York, with attached chart, "NEA Dues Money Being Spent to Fight Teachers in New York State (by State Association)," November 5, 1976; correspondence between NYSUT and NEA since Representative Assembly meeting, compiled April 22, 1976; letter from Hobart to NYSUT local presidents, urging membership to vote for withdrawal from NEA, January 6, 1976; flyer, "Did NYSUT really try?"; letters re NEA Project in New York; related correspondence
  - Representative Assembly, 1978 (Box 41, Folder 24)
    Resolutions and proposed constitutional amendments; Report on Implementation of 1977 Resolutions; information packet; program; special report from the Committee to Study the Position of Director at-Large; text of remarks by Ed Rogers (?) re finances; memo from Tom Hobart to confidential personnel re election results, April 10, 1978
  - Representative Assembly Expenses and Stipends, 1982 (Box 41, Folder 25)
    Calculations for stipends; list of officers receiving stipend checks, and amounts; invoices; related memos
  - NYSUT Conference Speeches, 1987 (Box 41, Folder 26)
    Remarks by Gordon Ambach, Commissioner of Education, at the Representative Assembly of the New York State United Teachers, "Strengthening the Teaching Profession and Education for Civic Responsibility," April 3, 1987; speech by Harold R. Newman, chairman, NYS Public Employment Relations Board (PERB), NYSUT Annual Convention, April 5, 1987; speech re Taylor Law by unnamed PERB official (Jerry Lefkowitz? referred to in Newman speech); speech by president of state federation (NYS AFL-CIO?)
  - Speech to Regents, n.d. (Box 41, Folder 27)
    Text of speech apparently by Commissioner of Education
  - NYSUT Presidents Mail Log, 1981 (Box 42, Folder 1)
    January-June 1981. Log sheets of incoming correspondence by date received, with sender's name and affiliation, and subject
  - NYSUT Presidents Mail Log, 1981 (Box 42, Folder 2)
    July-December 1981. Log sheets of incoming correspondence by date received, with sender's name and affiliation, and subject
  - NYSUT Presidents Mail Log, 1980 (Box 42, Folder 3)
    January-December 1980. Log sheets of incoming correspondence by date received, with sender's name and affiliation, and subject
  - NYSUT Local Presidents Mailings, 1978 (Box 42, Folder 4)
    October-December 1978. Outgoing correspondence mainly from NYSUT executive vice president Dan Sanders to local presidents, including information brochure on the Regents Competency Testing Program, materials from the Levittown United Teachers Defense Fund
  - NYSUT Local Presidents Mailings, 1978 (Box 42, Folder 5)
    June-September 1978. Outgoing correspondence mainly from NYSUT executive vice president Dan Sanders to local presidents, including legislative voting record, list of congressional candidates, and related materials for NYSUT Presidents Conference on Political Action
  - NYSUT Local Presidents Mailings, 1978 (Box 42, Folder 6)
    January-May 1978. Outgoing correspondence mainly from NYSUT executive vice president Dan Sanders to local presidents
  - NYSUT Local Presidents Mailings, 1977 (Box 42, Folder 7)
    April-December 1977. Outgoing correspondence mainly from NYSUT executive vice president Dan Sanders to local presidents
  - NYSUT Local Presidents Mailings, 1977 (Box 42, Folder 8)
    January-March 1977. Outgoing correspondence mainly from NYSUT executive vice president Dan Sanders to local presidents, including NYS Educational Conference Board Proposal for 1977-78 State Aid to Public Schools, January 1977
  - NYSUT Local Presidents Mailings, 1976 (Box 42, Folder 9)
    Outgoing correspondence to local presidents
  - NYSUT Local Presidents Mailings, 1975 (Box 42, Folder 10)
    January-April 1975. Outgoing correspondence to local presidents
  - NYSUT Local Presidents Mailings, 1975 (Box 42, Folder 11)
    May-August 1975. Outgoing correspondence to local presidents
  - NYSUT Local Presidents Mailings, 1974 (Box 42, Folder 12)
  - NYSUT Local Presidents Mailings, 1973 (Box 42, Folder 13)
  - NEA Representative Assembly (General Information), 1973 (Box 43, Folder 1)
    Program for 111th Annual Meeting (Portland, Oregon), National Education Association, 1973; National Education Association of the United States of America Resolutions and Other Actions, July 1972; NEA Proposed Amendments to the Bylaws & Standing Rules, 1973; American Federation of Teachers AFL-CIO Convention Call; New York State Delegation Business Meetings, NYSUT, 1973; NYSUT Hotline National Convention Notes, May 10, 1973; NEA/ADT Convention Information; memo to state association presidents from NEA president Catharine Barrett re logistics of convention lodging, June 7, 1973; correspondence re business items
  - Kozol Attack on Shanker, 1973 (Box 43, Folder 2)
    NYSUT State Caucus Meeting instruction sheet for tellers, sergeant-at-arms, credentials committee; Grass Roots Caucus, New York State United Teachers position on national merger; newspaper clipping from The Oregonian, July 2, 1973, "Radical Educator Heats Up NEA Convention," re Jonathan Kozol accusing Al Shanker of racist tactics
  - NEA Landrum-Griffen Problem (Tice), 1973 (Box 43, Folder 3)
    Yonkers Federation of Teachers resume of Walter Tice, candidate for NEA Executive Committee; letter to NYSUT general counsel Bernard Ashe from the U.S. Department of Labor re positive determination on NYSUT president Hobart's complaint that NEA is a labor organization subject to the Labor-Management Reporting and Disclosure Act of 1959, a concept to which NEA had expressed resistance, September 28, 1973; correspondence between Hobart and NEA president Catharine Barrett re legality of NEA Board of Directors in selecting at-large delegates, eligibility of Walter Tice to serve as officers; chronology of events leading to the removal of Walter Tice from NEA Executive Committee ballot; memo re presentation by Walter Tice's name before the NEA Bylaws and Rules Committee, June 30, 1973; notice to NEA by Hobart that he had initiated an investigation by U.S. Department of Labor of violation of rights of members under Labor-Management Reporting and Disclosure Act of 1959, July 20, 1973; copy of complaint, July 18, 1973
  - NEA Representative Assembly, Laura Wynn (Black Caucus), 1973 (Box 43, Folder 4)
    Statement of Laura Wynn
  - NEA Representative Assembly, Roll Call Vote re Merger, 1973 (Box 43, Folder 5)
    Tally by state
  - NEA Representative Assembly, State Contacts, 1973 (Box 43, Folder 6)
    List of contacts by state for NYSUT and NEA; correspondence with state presidents
  - NEA Representative Assembly, Tellers (NYSUT Delegation), 1973 (Box 43, Folder 7)
    Lists
  - NEA Representative Assembly (folder 1 of 2), 1974 (Box 43, Folder 8)
    Program for 112th Annual Meeting (Chicago, Illinois), "Crisis in Confidence 1974: Challenge for the Classroom," National Education Association, 1974; Report on the Resolutions of the National Education Association (Report of the Resolutions Committee); Reports on Implementation of Actions of the 1974 Representative Assembly; brochure re annual meeting; New Business Items Recommended by New York State Members of the NEA Resolutions Committee; NEA Representative Assembly New Business Items; letter to delegates from second vice president Toni Cortese, withdrawing candidacy for vice president, discussing issues with NEA leadership; newsletter, Unity Caucus special issue for New York State delegates, with lead article, "NEA Board of Directors Refuses to Expel Our Toni," June 29, 1974; newsletter, Teacher Forum, Voice of the Grassroots Caucus (NYSUT), special NEA Convention Issue, with lead article, "Lessons of the N.Y. State Merger"; announcements of candidacies for NEA executive positions by various state associations
  - NEA Representative Assembly (folder 1 of 2), 1974 (Box 43, Folder 9)
    Correspondence from state associations in anticipation of the 1974 Representative Assembly; calendar of events for New York State delegates; correspondence re candidates for NEA executive office; Unity Caucus 1974 Platform; Western Union telegram to labor and education writers, "AFT Charge That NEA Is Anti- Labor Is Self-Serving, NEA Head Says," June 11; proposed amendments to NEA bylaws; printed booklet, New Constitution and Bylaws of the National Education Association (effective as outlined in Transition Calendar), adopted by the 1973 NEA Representative Assembly
  - NEA Amendments, 1974 (Box 43, Folder 10)
    New Constitution and Bylaws, 1974
  - NEW Constitution Amendments, 1975 (Box 43, Folder 11)
    National Education Association Proposed Amendments to the Constitution, Bylaws & Standing Rules, 1975
  - NEA Representative Assembly (folder 1 of 3), 1975 (Box 43, Folder 12)
    Program for 113th Annual Meeting (Los Angeles, California), "Educational Strategies During an Economic Crisis," National Education Association, 1975; Velma Hill's Nominating Speech for Tom Hobart for the 2-Year Term on the NEA Executive Board; newspaper clipping, "4 Militant Liberals Seek Top Post in Teacher Group," Los Angeles Times, July 2, 1975; poster in support of James A. Harris for president of NEA; program for Critical Issues Conference: Educational Neglect; full list of candidates
  - NEA Representative Assembly (folder 2 of 3), 1975 (Box 43, Folder 13)
    Statement of James A. Harris, president of the National Education Association, on H.R. 2966 and S. 626, The Child and Family Services Act of 1975, before the Senate Subcommittee on Children and Youth and the House Select Committee on Education, Jun 5, 1975; Report to the NEA Board of Directors on DSN Project: Operation Uplift - Better Health for Better Learning" Activities for Implementing NEA Task Force on Drug Education Recommendations, June 1975; NEA Governance Documents, 1974-75; Resolutions and Other Actions, July 1974; Report on the Resolutions of the National Education Association (Report of the Resolutions Committee, 113th meeting), July 5-8. 1975; Code of Ethics of the Education Profession, adopted by the NEA Representative Assembly, July 1968, amended June 1972; Proposed Revision of the Code of Ethics of the Education Profession, for presentation to the 1975 Representative Assembly; Reports of Committees, Councils, and Task Forces, 1974-75, presented to the Fifty-Fourth Representative Assembly of the National Education Association, July 2-8, 1975, Los Angeles, California; NEA Preliminary Report Program Budget, Fiscal Year 1975-76, May 15, 1975; Project 1975: Educational Neglect: Report and Working Papers, Thirteenth National Conference on Civil and Human Rights in Education, February 15-18, 1975
  - NEA Representative Assembly (folder 2 of 3), 1975 (Box 43, Folder 14)
    Envelope marked Unofficial Minutes of Meeting with TYH [Tom Hobart] and Others with Harris/Ferrone at the 1975 NEA Convention, containing documents, NEA Convention - 1975 Summary of Conversations with Harris, Ferrone, and NYSUT People, Los Angeles, California, re conditions for support of Harris by New York delegation, and handwritten notes; flyers supporting Tom Hobart for two-year term on NEA Executive Committee; Hobart schedules; NYSUT publication, The True Discovery: A Pictorial Bicentennial Essay; "Hard Times, Brighter Days," address by Terry Sanford, President of Duke University, to the NEA, July 7, 1975; biography of Sanford; speech by Harvey Zorbaugh, Jr., executive director of the Coalition of American Public Employees; partial Hobart speech and handwritten notes; press releases; campaign guidelines; voting schedule; NEA Proposed Amendments to the Constitution, bylaws & Standing Rules, 1975
  - NEA Representative Assembly Candidates File, 1975 (Box 43, Folder 15)
    Report of the 1975 NEA Delegation to the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics; apparent form letter from James A. Harris seeking support for reelection as NEA president, and attached return postcard, with letter from Tom Hobart to Harris's assistant, advising him that he needed to hear from Harris directly, March 5, 1975; materials for candidate for NEA president, Bryan Stevens of California; campaign materials for candidates for other NEA offices
  - NEA Memorandum to State Presidents, 1975 (Box 43, Folder 16)
    October 2, 1975. Memo re summary of changes to agreement NEA and two employee bargaining units; memo re NEA and NEA Student relationship
  - NEA Representative Assembly, 1976 (Box 43, Folder 17)
    Program for 114th Annual Meeting (Miami Beach, Florida), "America's Third Century: The Teachers' Unfinished Agenda," NEA, 1976; statements by NEA president John Royer; Address of Terry Herndon, NEA Executive Director; NEA Review Board Procedures: Rules for Impeachment, Censure, Suspension, Expulsion, Review of Governance Actions; list of teacher delegate to the Democratic National Convention; financial reports; memo to presidents of affiliated state and local associations re allocation of ethnic-minority representation, December 1975
  - World Confederation of Organizations of the Teaching Profession (WCOTP), 1976-1977 (Box 43, Folder 18)
    Program for Regional Conference 1976 of the Gambia Teachers Union; Report of the First WCOTP Pacific Regional Conference, Fiji, January 1976; notes of dues payment, January 1977
  - World Confederation of Organizations of the Teaching Profession (WCOTP), 1976 (Box 43, Folder 19)